<?xml version="1.0"?>
<visitor id="sam">
<head>Sam Firth</head>
<p>Sam er en venn av Trond, Trond seilte med Bjørn Jordan når han seilte sin
karbia tur sist. Sam hadde blitt tipset av Trond om at det var mulig å være
med oss på en eller flere "legs" som han sier.</p>

<p>Det passer visst bra, for han har tenkt å skrive et film manus om livet
på en "yacht"! Ragnar var kjapt frempå med ideen om at vi kom til å stå i
rulleteksten i en fremtidig film.. Var det noen tvil om at han kunne være
med?!? </p>

<p>Det er ikke bestemt hvilken etappe han skal være med på, men det blir
sannsynligvis enten Brest - Spania eller Lisboa - Kanariøyene.</p>

<p>Sam om seg selv</p>
<p> am 28 years old (born 9.7.1974). I was born and raised in London. I.m in my final year of an MA in screenwriting at the Northern Film School in Leeds which is where I met Trond. Trond told me about this trip because my final year project is set on a yacht and I haven't been sailing since I was a child (I am going to go for a weekend to practice this summer). Being on a boat for a couple of weeks and sailing for such a long distance will be perfect.

In my film two sisters end up stranded on a boat and neither of them know how to sail. The story is about sibling rivalry and what happens to teenagers when there are no boundaries.

Apart from writing and watching films, I like dancing, jogging, trekking, and cooking big meals for my friends. I was born and raised in London. I have been writing for four years and have worked in the UK film industry for the last seven (on film festivals, as an assistant producer, and as a script editor).

 I currently live in a village in the Yorkshire hills and am renovating a house for my dad. It all seems very small in comparison to London but I.m getting lots of work done. I visited Kristiansand once last September to see Trond but I still don.t really speak a word of Norwegian so being the only English person on the boat should be interesting! I am really looking forward to the trip. The film script is a brilliant excuse to have an adventure!

</p>


</visitor>
