Around the world with Staale and Rozinante ended dramatically.
But exciting events happened earlier.
He was alone day and night, two months alone on Rozinante.
But one week after he left Australia he visited an island...
So we found Auckland Island.
It's here the Albatrosses live. It's here they get born!
And then they fly out on the ocean.
This place is a very safe place to anchor.
The island was full of strange animals, not people.
It was quite funny.
I spent about a week on the island and celebrated new years eve.
Along with the albatrosses and a group of not-hospitable seals.
The sun is very strong here. Because we are so close to Antarctica.
Now we're going in and look at this beach.
As soon as Staale placed his foot on the island, the welcome-comitee
arrived.
This meeting didn't actually turn out te be the touching encounter -
- between the inhabitant and the sailor as Staale hoped.
Soon it was very clear who was the owner of this beach.
I think he's decided to kill me.
The intruder has to find an alternate passage into the island.
The reason why I'm looking like a combination of a stoneage man-
-and a modern soldier, is because we have declared war on the
combat-seal.
And he's not very small.
That's why we had to walk through the jungle.
He attacked when we tried to go through the beach.
And I don't know how such animal thinks.
In fact I've never been more scared in my life when he attacked
the dingy!
But now I'm armed.
The expedition finds a cabin.
We have found a cabin with food for shipwrecked.
I think it's time to replace some of it!
It doesn't seem to be updated very often.
"Left by members of seafarer April 1977".
"Visited by Finesse of Tasman. From Hobart, Tasmania
February 1988".
"Pirate Ship Rozinante, Norway. 01/01-2006. Staale."
Bye, bye Auckland Island. Now we're off!
You'll be in our back for 40 days, before we get to Cape Horn.
You'll just stay here and be a strict nature's reserve.
Now we've visited you without getting a penalty. And it's a bit
amusing!
Now we're going to cross the date-line. This is the first time.
The time is 02:31, 8th of January.
Outside it's strong gale.
Oops! I didn't noticed we crossed.
Now it's says west instead of east.